A Questlove Jawn.
Summer of Soul (...Or, When the Revolution Could Not Be Televised) is a
music, documentary, history film directed by Questlove.
During the same summer as Woodstock, over 300,000 people attended the Harlem Cultural Festival,
celebrating African American music and culture, and promoting Black pride and unity.
The footage from the festival sat in a basement, unseen for over 50 years,
keeping this incredible event in America's history lost — until now.
Self, played by Stevie Wonder.
Self - Artist, played by Lin-Manuel Miranda.
Self - Artist, played by Chris Rock.
Self - Harlem Cultural Festival Producer & Host
(archive footage), played by Tony Lawrence.
Self (archive footage), played by Nina Simone.
Self (archive footage), played by B.B. King.
Summer of Soul (...or, When the Revolution Could Not Be Televised) is a 2021 American independent documentary film
about the 1969 Harlem Cultural Festival, directed by Ahmir "Questlove" Thompson in his directorial debut.
It had its world premiere at the 2021 Sundance Film Festival on January 28, 2021, where it
won the Grand Jury Prize and Audience Award in the documentary categories.
It had a limited theatrical release in the U.S.
by Searchlight Pictures on June 25, 2021, before expanding and
being released for streaming on Hulu the next weekend.
The second half of the movie's title is taken from the 1970 poem and song "The
Revolution Will Not Be Televised", written by Gil Scott-Heron.
It offered a sharp and satirical critique of the media's lack of coverage of civil rights activism and the
reality of change and revolution taking place in the streets and on campuses across America.
The film received acclaim from critics, with particular praise
given to the restoration of the footage used.
It won numerous awards, including Best Documentary Feature at the 6th Critics' Choice Documentary Awards, where it won in all six categories in which it was nominated, Best
Documentary at the 75th British Academy Film Awards, Best Documentary Feature at the 94th Academy Awards, and Best Music Film at the 64th Annual Grammy Awards.
It has been considered one of the best films of the 21st century.
The film explores themes of jazz, empowerment, blues,
civil rights, rhythm and blues (r&b).
The tone is lighthearted.